<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> A written validation protocol should be established that specifies how  validation of a particular process will be conducted. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> The protocol should be reviewed  and approved by the quality unit(s) and other designated units. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> The validation protocol should specify critical process steps and acceptance  criteria as well as the type of validation to be conducted (e.g. retrospective,  prospective, concurrent) and the number of process runs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> A validation report that cross-references the validation protocol should be  prepared, summarising the results obtained, commenting on any deviations observed,  and drawing the appropriate conclusions, including recommending changes to correct  deficiencies. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Any variations from the validation protocol should be documented with  appropriate justification. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> Before starting process validation activities, appropriate qualification of  critical equipment and ancillary systems should be completed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> Qualification is usually  carried out by conducting the following activities, individually or combined: </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> Design Qualification (DQ): documented verification that the proposed design  of the facilities, equipment, or systems is suitable for the intended purpose. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> Installation Qualification (IQ): documented verification that the equipment or  systems, as installed or modified, comply with the approved design, the  manufacturer’s recommendations and/or user requirements. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> Operational Qualification (OQ): documented verification that the equipment  or systems, as installed or modified, perform as intended throughout the  anticipated operating ranges. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> Performance Qualification (PQ): documented verification that the equipment  and ancillary systems, as connected together, can perform effectively and  reproducibly based on the approved process method and specifications. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> Process Validation (PV) is the documented evidence that the process, operated  within established parameters, can perform effectively and reproducibly to produce an  intermediate or API meeting its predetermined specifications and quality attributes. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> There are three approaches to validation. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> Prospective validation is the  preferred approach, but there are exceptions where the other approaches can be used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> These approaches and their applicability are listed below. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> Prospective validation should normally be performed for all API processes as  defined in 12.12. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> Prospective validation performed on an API process should be  completed before the commercial distribution of the final drug product manufactured  from that API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> Concurrent validation can be conducted when data from replicate production  runs are unavailable because only a limited number of API batches have been  produced, API batches are produced infrequently, or API batches are produced by a  validated process that has been modified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Prior to the completion of concurrent  validation, batches can be released and used in final drug product for commercial  distribution based on thorough monitoring and testing of the API batches. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> An exception can be made for retrospective validation for well established  processes that have been used without significant changes to API quality due to  changes in raw materials, equipment, systems, facilities, or the production process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> This validation approach may be used where: </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> Critical quality attributes and critical process parameters have been identified;  (2) Appropriate in-process acceptance criteria and controls have been established;  (3) There have not been significant process/product failures attributable to causes  other than operator error or equipment failures unrelated to equipment suitability; and  (4) Impurity profiles have been established for the existing API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Batches selected for retrospective validation should be representative of all  batches made during the review period, including any batches that failed to meet  specifications, and should be sufficient in number to demonstrate process consistency. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> Retained samples can be tested to obtain data to retrospectively validate the process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> The number of process runs for validation should depend on the complexity of  the process or the magnitude of the process change being considered. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> For prospective  and concurrent validation, three consecutive successful production batches should be  used as a guide, but there may be situations where additional process runs are  warranted to prove consistency of the process (e.g., complex API processes or API  processes with prolonged completion times). </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> For retrospective validation, generally   37 data from ten to thirty consecutive batches should be examined to assess process  consistency, but fewer batches can be examined if justified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> Critical process parameters should be controlled and monitored during process  validation studies. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> Process parameters unrelated to quality, such as variables  controlled to minimize energy consumption or equipment use, need not be included in  the process validation. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> Process validation should confirm that the impurity profile for each API is  within the limits specified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> The impurity profile should be comparable to or better  than historical data and, where applicable, the profile determined during process  development or for batches used for pivotal clinical and toxicological studies. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Systems and processes should be periodically evaluated to verify that they are  still operating in a valid manner. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> Where no significant changes have been made to the  system or process, and a quality review confirms that the system or process is  consistently producing material meeting its specifications, there is normally no need  for revalidation. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> Cleaning procedures should normally be validated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> In general, cleaning  validation should be directed to situations or process steps where contamination or  carryover of materials poses the greatest risk to API quality. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> For example, in early  production it may be unnecessary to validate equipment cleaning procedures where  residues are removed by subsequent purification steps. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> Validation of cleaning procedures should reflect actual equipment usage  patterns. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> If various APIs or intermediates are manufactured in the same equipment  and the equipment is cleaned by the same process, a representative intermediate or  API can be selected for cleaning validation. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> This selection should be based on the  solubility and difficulty of cleaning and the calculation of residue limits based on  potency, toxicity, and stability. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> The cleaning validation protocol should describe the equipment to be cleaned,  procedures, materials, acceptable cleaning levels, parameters to be monitored and  controlled, and analytical methods. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> The protocol should also indicate the type of  samples to be obtained and how they are collected and labelled. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Sampling should include swabbing, rinsing, or alternative methods (e.g., direct  extraction), as appropriate, to detect both insoluble and soluble residues. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> The  sampling methods used should be capable of quantitatively measuring levels of  residues remaining on the equipment surfaces after cleaning. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> Swab sampling may be  impractical when product contact surfaces are not easily accessible due to equipment  design and/or process limitations (e.g., inner surfaces of hoses, transfer pipes, reactor  tanks with small ports or handling toxic materials, and small intricate equipment such  as micronizers and microfluidizers). </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> Validated analytical methods having sensitivity to detect residues or  contaminants should be used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> The detection limit for each analytical method should  be sufficiently sensitive to detect the established acceptable level of the residue or  contaminant. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> The method’s attainable recovery level should be established. </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> Residue  limits should be practical, achievable, verifiable and based on the most deleterious  residue. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> Limits can be established based on the minimum known pharmacological,  toxicological, or physiological activity of the API or its most deleterious component. </sentence>
</sentences>
