<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> Quality should be the responsibility of all persons involved in manufacturing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Each manufacturer should establish, document, and implement an effective  system for managing quality that involves the active participation of management and  appropriate manufacturing personnel. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> The system for managing quality should encompass the organisational  structure, procedures, processes and resources, as well as activities necessary to  ensure confidence that the API will meet its intended specifications for quality and  purity. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> All quality related activities should be defined and documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> There should be a quality unit(s) that is independent of production and that  fulfills both quality assurance (QA) and quality control (QC) responsibilities. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> This can  be in the form of separate QA and QC units or a single individual or group, depending  upon the size and structure of the organization. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> The persons authorised to release intermediates and APIs should be specified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> All quality related activities should be recorded at the time they are performed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> Any deviation from established procedures should be documented and  explained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10">  Critical deviations should be investigated, and the investigation and its  conclusions should be documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> No materials should be released or used before the satisfactory completion of  evaluation by the quality unit(s) unless there are appropriate systems in place to allow  for such use (e.g. release under quarantine as described in Section 10.20 or the use of  raw materials or intermediates pending completion of evaluation). </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> Procedures should exist for notifying responsible management in a timely  manner of regulatory inspections, serious GMP deficiencies, product defects and  related actions (e.g. quality related complaints, recalls, regulatory actions, etc.). </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> The quality unit(s) should be involved in all quality-related matters. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> The quality unit(s) should review and approve all appropriate quality-related  documents. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> The main responsibilities of the independent quality unit(s) should not be  delegated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> In order to verify compliance with the principles of GMP for APIs, regular  internal audits should be performed in accordance with an approved schedule. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> Audit findings and corrective actions should be documented and brought to  the attention of responsible management of the firm. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> Agreed corrective actions should  be completed in a timely and effective manner. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Regular quality reviews of APIs should be conducted with the objective of  verifying the consistency of the process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> Such reviews should normally be conducted  and documented annually and should include at least: </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> A review of critical in-process control and critical API test results;  - A review of all batches that failed to meet established specification(s);  - A review of all critical deviations or non-conformances and related investigations;  - A review of any changes carried out to the processes or analytical methods;  - A review of results of the stability monitoring program;  - A review of all quality-related returns, complaints and recalls; and  - A review of adequacy of corrective actions. </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> The results of this review should be evaluated and an assessment made of  whether corrective action or any revalidation should be undertaken. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Reasons for such  corrective action should be documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> Agreed corrective actions should be  completed in a timely and effective manner. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> There should be an adequate number of personnel qualified by appropriate  education, training and/or experience to perform and supervise the manufacture of  intermediates and APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> The responsibilities of all personnel engaged in the manufacture of  intermediates and APIs should be specified in writing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> Training should be regularly conducted by qualified individuals and should  cover, at a minimum, the particular operations that the employee performs and GMP  as it relates to the employee's functions. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> Records of training should be maintained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> Training should be periodically assessed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> Personnel should practice good sanitation and health habits. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Personnel should wear clean clothing suitable for the manufacturing activity  with which they are involved and this clothing should be changed when appropriate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> Additional protective apparel, such as head, face, hand, and arm coverings, should be  worn when necessary, to protect intermediates and APIs from contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> Personnel should avoid direct contact with intermediates or APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> Smoking, eating, drinking, chewing and the storage of food should be  restricted to certain designated areas separate from the manufacturing areas. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> Personnel suffering from an infectious disease or having open lesions on the  exposed surface of the body should not engage in activities that could result in  compromising the quality of APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> Any person shown at any time (either by medical  examination or supervisory observation) to have an apparent illness or open lesions  should be excluded from activities where the health condition could adversely affect  the quality of the APIs until the condition is corrected or qualified medical personnel  determine that the person's inclusion would not jeopardize the safety or quality of the  APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Consultants advising on the manufacture and control of intermediates or APIs  should have sufficient education, training, and experience, or any combination  thereof, to advise on the subject for which they are retained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> Records should be maintained stating the name, address, qualifications, and  type of service provided by these consultants. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> Buildings and facilities used in the manufacture of intermediates and APIs  should be located, designed, and constructed to facilitate cleaning, maintenance, and  operations as appropriate to the type and stage of manufacture. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> Facilities should also  be designed to minimize potential contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Where microbiological  specifications have been established for the intermediate or API, facilities should also  be designed to limit exposure to objectionable microbiological contaminants as  appropriate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> Buildings and facilities should have adequate space for the orderly placement  of equipment and materials to prevent mix-ups and contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> Where the equipment itself (e.g., closed or contained systems) provides  adequate protection of the material, such equipment can be located outdoors. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> The flow of materials and personnel through the building or facilities should be  designed to prevent mix-ups or contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> There should be defined areas or other control systems for the following  activities: </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> Receipt, identification, sampling, and quarantine of incoming materials,  pending release or rejection;  - Quarantine before release or rejection of intermediates and APIs;  - Sampling of intermediates and APIs;  - Holding rejected materials before further disposition (e.g., return,  reprocessing or destruction)  - Storage of released materials;  - Production operations;  - Packaging and labelling operations; and  - Laboratory operations. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> Adequate, clean washing and toilet facilities should be provided for personnel. </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> These washing facilities should be equipped with hot and cold water as appropriate,   13 soap or detergent, air driers or single service towels. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> The washing and toilet facilities  should be separate from, but easily accessible to, manufacturing areas. </sentence>
</sentences>
