<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> The results of such assessments should be taken into consideration in the disposition  of the material produced. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Records of contamination events should be maintained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> Shared (multi-product) equipment may warrant additional testing after  cleaning between product campaigns, as appropriate, to minimize the risk of cross- contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> Harvesting steps, either to remove cells or cellular components or to collect  cellular components after disruption, should be performed in equipment and areas  designed to minimize the risk of contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Harvest and purification procedures that remove or inactivate the producing  organism, cellular debris and media components (while minimizing degradation,  contamination, and loss of quality) should be adequate to ensure that the intermediate  or API is recovered with consistent quality. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> All equipment should be properly cleaned and, as appropriate, sanitized after  use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> Multiple successive batching without cleaning can be used if intermediate or API  quality is not compromised. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> If open systems are used, purification should be performed under  environmental conditions appropriate for the preservation of product quality. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> Additional controls, such as the use of dedicated chromatography resins or  additional testing, may be appropriate if equipment is to be used for multiple  products. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> See the ICH Guideline Q5A Quality of Biotechnological Products: Viral  Safety Evaluation of Biotechnology Products Derived from Cell Lines of Human or  Animal Origin for more specific information. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> Viral removal and viral inactivation steps are critical processing steps for  some processes and should be performed within their validated parameters. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> Appropriate precautions should be taken to prevent potential viral  contamination from pre-viral to post-viral removal/inactivation steps. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> Therefore, open  processing should be performed in areas that are separate from other processing  activities and have separate air handling units. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> The same equipment is not normally used for different purification steps. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> However, if the same equipment is to be used, the equipment should be appropriately  cleaned and sanitized before reuse. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> Appropriate precautions should be taken to  prevent potential virus carry-over (e.g. through equipment or environment) from  previous steps. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Not all the controls in the previous sections of this Guide are appropriate for  the manufacture of a new API for investigational use during its development. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> Section  19 provides specific guidance unique to these circumstances. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> The controls used in the manufacture of APIs for use in clinical trials should  be consistent with the stage of development of the drug product incorporating the  API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> Process and test procedures should be flexible to provide for changes as  knowledge of the process increases and clinical testing of a drug product progresses  from pre-clinical stages through clinical stages. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Once drug development reaches the  stage where the API is produced for use in drug products intended for clinical trials,  manufacturers should ensure that APIs are manufactured in suitable facilities using  appropriate production and control procedures to ensure the quality of the API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> Appropriate GMP concepts should be applied in the production of APIs for  use in clinical trials with a suitable mechanism of approval of each batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> A quality unit(s) independent from production should be established for the  approval or rejection of each batch of API for use in clinical trials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> Some of the testing functions commonly performed by the quality unit(s) can  be performed within other organizational units. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> Quality measures should include a system for testing of raw materials,  packaging materials, intermediates, and APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> Process and quality problems should be evaluated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> Labelling for APIs intended for use in clinical trials should be appropriately  controlled and should identify the material as being for investigational use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> During all phases of clinical development, including the use of small-scale  facilities or laboratories to manufacture batches of APIs for use in clinical trials,  procedures should be in place to ensure that equipment is calibrated, clean and  suitable for its intended use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> Procedures for the use of facilities should ensure that materials are handled in  a manner that minimizes the risk of contamination and cross-contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Raw materials used in production of APIs for use in clinical trials should be  evaluated by testing, or received with a supplier’s analysis and subjected to identity  testing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> When a material is considered hazardous, a supplier's analysis should suffice. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> In some instances, the suitability of a raw material can be determined before  use based on acceptability in small-scale reactions (i.e., use testing) rather than on  analytical testing alone. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> The production of APIs for use in clinical trials should be documented in  laboratory notebooks, batch records, or by other appropriate means. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> These documents  should include information on the use of production materials, equipment, processing,  and scientific observations. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> Investigations into yield variations are not expected. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Process validation for the production of APIs for use in clinical trials is  normally inappropriate, where a single API batch is produced or where process  changes during API development make batch replication difficult or inexact. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> The  combination of controls, calibration, and, where appropriate, equipment qualification  assures API quality during this development phase. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> Process validation should be conducted in accordance with Section 12 when  batches are produced for commercial use, even when such batches are produced on a  pilot or small scale. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> Changes are expected during development, as knowledge is gained and the  production is scaled up. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Every change in the production, specifications, or test  procedures should be adequately recorded. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> While analytical methods performed to evaluate a batch of API for clinical  trials may not yet be validated, they should be scientifically sound. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> A system for retaining reserve samples of all batches should be in place. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> This  system should ensure that a sufficient quantity of each reserve sample is retained for  an appropriate length of time after approval, termination, or discontinuation of an  application. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> Expiry and retest dating as defined in Section 11.6 applies to existing APIs  used in clinical trials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> For new APIs, Section 11.6 does not normally apply in early  stages of clinical trials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> A system should be in place to ensure that information gained during the  development and the manufacture of APIs for use in clinical trials is documented and  available. </sentence>
</sentences>
