<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> Deviations from approved standards of calibration on critical instruments  should be investigated to determine if these could have had an impact on the quality  of the intermediate(s) or API(s) manufactured using this equipment since the last  successful calibration. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> GMP related computerized systems should be validated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> The depth and scope  of validation depends on the diversity, complexity and criticality of the computerized  application. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> Appropriate installation qualification and operational qualification should  demonstrate the suitability of computer hardware and software to perform assigned  tasks. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Commercially available software that has been qualified does not require the  same level of testing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> If an existing system was not validated at time of installation, a  retrospective validation could be conducted if appropriate documentation is available. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> Computerized systems should have sufficient controls to prevent unauthorized  access or changes to data. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> There should be controls to prevent omissions in data (e.g.  system turned off and data not captured). </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> There should be a record of any data change  made, the previous entry, who made the change, and when the change was made. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> Written procedures should be available for the operation and maintenance of  computerized systems. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> Where critical data are being entered manually, there should be an additional  check on the accuracy of the entry. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> This can be done by a second operator or by the  system itself. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> Incidents related to computerized systems that could affect the quality of  intermediates or APIs or the reliability of records or test results should be recorded  and investigated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> Changes to the computerized system should be made according to a change  procedure and should be formally authorized, documented and tested. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> Records should  be kept of all changes, including modifications and enhancements made to the   18 hardware, software and any other critical component of the system. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> These records  should demonstrate that the system is maintained in a validated state. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> If system breakdowns or failures would result in the permanent loss of  records, a back-up system should be provided. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> A means of ensuring data protection  should be established for all computerized systems. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Data can be recorded by a second means in addition to the computer system. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> All documents related to the manufacture of intermediates or APIs should be  prepared, reviewed, approved and distributed according to written procedures. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> Such  documents can be in paper or electronic form. </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> The issuance, revision, superseding and withdrawal of all documents should  be controlled with maintenance of revision histories. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> A procedure should be established for retaining all appropriate documents  (e.g., development history reports, scale-up reports, technical transfer reports, process  validation reports, training records, production records, control records, and  distribution records). </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> The retention periods for these documents should be specified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> All production, control, and distribution records should be retained for at least  1 year after the expiry date of the batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> For APIs with retest dates, records should be  retained for at least 3 years after the batch is completely distributed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> When entries are made in records, these should be made indelibly in spaces  provided for such entries, directly after performing the activities, and should identify  the person making the entry. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> Corrections to entries should be dated and signed and  leave the original entry still readable. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> During the retention period, originals or copies of records should be readily  available at the establishment where the activities described in such records occurred. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> Records that can be promptly retrieved from another location by electronic or other  means are acceptable. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> Specifications, instructions, procedures, and records can be retained either as  originals or as true copies such as photocopies, microfilm, microfiche, or other  accurate reproductions of the original records. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Where reduction techniques such as  microfilming or electronic records are used, suitable retrieval equipment and a means  to produce a hard copy should be readily available. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> Specifications should be established and documented for raw materials,  intermediates where necessary, APIs, and labelling and packaging materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> In  addition, specifications may be appropriate for certain other materials, such as process  aids, gaskets, or other materials used during the production of intermediates or APIs   19 that could critically impact on quality. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> Acceptance criteria should be established and  documented for in-process controls. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> If electronic signatures are used on documents, they should be authenticated  and secure. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> Records of major equipment use, cleaning, sanitization and/or sterilization and  maintenance should show the date, time (if appropriate), product, and batch number  of each batch processed in the equipment, and the person who performed the cleaning  and maintenance. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> If equipment is dedicated to manufacturing one intermediate or API, then  individual equipment records are not necessary if batches of the intermediate or API  follow in traceable sequence. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> In cases where dedicated equipment is employed, the  records of cleaning, maintenance, and use can be part of the batch record or  maintained separately. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> Records should be maintained including: </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> The name of the manufacturer, identity and quantity of each shipment of each  batch of raw materials, intermediates or labelling and packaging materials for  API's; the name of the supplier; the supplier's control number(s), if known, or  other identification number; the number allocated on receipt; and the date of  receipt;  - The results of any test or examination performed and the conclusions derived  from this;  - Records tracing the use of materials;  - Documentation of the examination and review of API labelling and packaging  materials for conformity with established specifications; and  - The final decision regarding rejected raw materials, intermediates or API  labelling and packaging materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Master (approved) labels should be maintained for comparison to issued  labels. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> To ensure uniformity from batch to batch, master production instructions for  each intermediate and API should be prepared, dated, and signed by one person and  independently checked, dated, and signed by a person in the quality unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> The name of the intermediate or API being manufactured and an identifying  document reference code, if applicable;  - A complete list of raw materials and intermediates designated by names or  codes sufficiently specific to identify any special quality characteristics;  - An accurate statement of the quantity or ratio of each raw material or  intermediate to be used, including the unit of measure. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> Where the quantity is  not fixed, the calculation for each batch size or rate of production should be  included. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> Variations to quantities should be included where they are justified;  - The production location and major production equipment to be used;  - Detailed production instructions, including the:  - sequences to be followed,  - ranges of process parameters to be used,  - sampling instructions and in-process controls with their acceptance criteria,  where appropriate,  - time limits for completion of individual processing steps and/or the total  process, where appropriate; and  - expected yield ranges at appropriate phases of processing or time;  - Where appropriate, special notations and precautions to be followed, or cross  references to these; and  - The instructions for storage of the intermediate or API to assure its suitability  for use, including the labelling and packaging materials and special storage  conditions with time limits, where appropriate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> Batch production records should be prepared for each intermediate and API  and should include complete information relating to the production and control of  each batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> The batch production record should be checked before issuance to assure  that it is the correct version and a legible accurate reproduction of the appropriate  master production instruction. </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> If the batch production record is produced from a  separate part of the master document, that document should include a reference to the  current master production instruction being used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> These records should be numbered with a unique batch or identification  number, dated and signed when issued. </sentence>
</sentences>
