<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> Records should be maintained of each primary reference standard’s  storage and use in accordance with the supplier’s recommendations. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Primary  reference standards obtained from an officially recognised source are normally used  without testing if stored under conditions consistent with the supplier’s  recommendations. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> Where a primary reference standard is not available from an officially  recognized source, an “in-house primary standard” should be established. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> Appropriate  testing should be performed to establish fully the identity and purity of the primary  reference standard. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Appropriate documentation of this testing should be maintained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> Secondary reference standards should be appropriately prepared, identified,  tested, approved, and stored. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> The suitability of each batch of secondary reference   32 standard should be determined prior to first use by comparing against a primary  reference standard. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> Each batch of secondary reference standard should be periodically  requalified in accordance with a written protocol. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> For each batch of intermediate and API, appropriate laboratory tests should be  conducted to determine conformance to specifications. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> An impurity profile describing the identified and unidentified impurities  present in a typical batch produced by a specific controlled production process should  normally be established for each API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> The impurity profile should include the identity  or some qualitative analytical designation (e.g. retention time), the range of each  impurity observed, and classification of each identified impurity (e.g. inorganic,  organic, solvent). </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> The impurity profile is normally dependent upon the production  process and origin of the API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> Impurity profiles are normally not necessary for APIs  from herbal or animal tissue origin. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> Biotechnology considerations are covered in ICH  Guideline Q6B. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> The impurity profile should be compared at appropriate intervals against the  impurity profile in the regulatory submission or compared against historical data in  order to detect changes to the API resulting from modifications in raw materials,  equipment operating parameters, or the production process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> Appropriate microbiological tests should be conducted on each batch of  intermediate and API where microbial quality is specified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> Authentic Certificates of Analysis should be issued for each batch of  intermediate or API on request. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> Information on the name of the intermediate or API including where  appropriate its grade, the batch number, and the date of release should be provided on  the Certificate of Analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> For intermediates or APIs with an expiry date, the expiry  date should be provided on the label and Certificate of Analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> For intermediates or  APIs with a retest date, the retest date should be indicated on the label and/or  Certificate of Analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> The Certificate should list each test performed in accordance with compendial  or customer requirements, including the acceptance limits, and the numerical results  obtained (if test results are numerical). </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> Certificates should be dated and signed by authorised personnel of the quality  unit(s) and should show the name, address and telephone number of the original  manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Where the analysis has been carried out by a repacker or reprocessor,   33 the Certificate of Analysis should show the name, address and telephone number of  the repacker/ reprocessor and a reference to the name of the original manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> If new Certificates are issued by or on behalf of repackers/ reprocessors,  agents or brokers, these Certificates should show the name, address and telephone  number of the laboratory that performed the analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> They should also contain a  reference to the name and address of the original manufacturer and to the original  batch Certificate, a copy of which should be attached. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> A documented, on-going testing program should be designed to monitor the  stability characteristics of APIs, and the results should be used to confirm appropriate  storage conditions and retest or expiry dates. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> The test procedures used in stability testing should be validated and be  stability indicating. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> Stability samples should be stored in containers that simulate the market  container. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> For example, if the API is marketed in bags within fiber drums, stability  samples can be packaged in bags of the same material and in smaller-scale drums of  similar or identical material composition to the market drums. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> Normally the first three commercial production batches should be placed on  the stability monitoring program to confirm the retest or expiry date. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> However, where  data from previous studies show that the API is expected to remain stable for at least  two years, fewer than three batches can be used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Thereafter, at least one batch per year of API manufactured (unless none is  produced that year) should be added to the stability monitoring program and tested at  least annually to confirm the stability. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> For APIs with short shelf-lives, testing should be done more frequently. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> For  example, for those biotechnological/biologic and other APIs with shelf-lives of one  year or less, stability samples should be obtained and should be tested monthly for the  first three months, and at three month intervals after that. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> When data exist that  confirm that the stability of the API is not compromised, elimination of specific test  intervals (e.g. 9 month testing) can be considered. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> Where appropriate, the stability storage conditions should be consistent with  the ICH guidelines on stability. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> When an intermediate is intended to be transferred outside the control of the  manufacturer’s material management system and an expiry or retest date is assigned,  supporting stability information should be available (e.g. published data, test results). </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Common practice is to use a retest date, not an expiration date. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> Preliminary API expiry or retest dates can be based on pilot scale batches if  (1) the pilot batches employ a method of manufacture and procedure that simulates  the final process to be used on a commercial manufacturing scale; and (2) the quality  of the API represents the material to be made on a commercial scale. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> A representative sample should be taken for the purpose of performing a  retest. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> The packaging and holding of reserve samples is for the purpose of potential  future evaluation of the quality of batches of API and not for future stability testing  purposes. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Appropriately identified reserve samples of each API batch should be retained  for one year after the expiry date of the batch assigned by the manufacturer, or for  three years after distribution of the batch, whichever is the longer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> For APIs with  retest dates, similar reserve samples should be retained for three years after the batch  is completely distributed by the manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> The reserve sample should be stored in the same packaging system in which  the API is stored or in one that is equivalent to or more protective than the marketed  packaging system. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> Sufficient quantities should be retained to conduct at least two full  compendial analyses or, when there is no pharmacopoeial monograph, two full  specification analyses. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> The company's overall policy, intentions, and approach to validation,  including the validation of production processes, cleaning procedures, analytical  methods, in-process control test procedures, computerized systems, and persons  responsible for design, review, approval and documentation of each validation phase,  should be documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> The critical parameters/attributes should normally be identified during the  development stage or from historical data, and the ranges necessary for the  reproducible operation should be defined. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> This should include: </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> Defining the API in terms of its critical product attributes;  - Identifying process parameters that could affect the critical quality attributes  of the API;   35 - Determining the range for each critical process parameter expected to be used  during routine manufacturing and process control. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> Validation should extend to those operations determined to be critical to the  quality and purity of the API. </sentence>
</sentences>
