<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <meta>
        <name>Eudralex</name>
        <description>EU regulation for the pharmaceutical industry</description>
        <body>EMEA</body>
        <version>1.0</version>
        <published_on>2007</published_on>
    </meta>
    <content>
        <chapter
                title="CHAPTER 5   PRODUCTION">CHAPTER 5   PRODUCTION<section
                    title="Principle">Principle<paragraph paraNum=""> operations must follow clearly defined procedures; they must comply with the principles of Good Manufacturing Practice in order to obtain products of the requisite quality and be in accordance with the relevant manufacturing and marketing authorisations</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section title=" General"> General<paragraph paraNum="5.1"> Production should be performed and supervised by competent people. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.2"> All handling of materials and products, such as receipt and quarantine, sampling, storage, labelling, dispensing, processing, packaging and distribution should be done in accordance with written procedures or instructions and, where necessary, recorded. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.3"> All incoming materials should be checked to ensure that the consignment corresponds to the order. Containers should be cleaned where necessary and labelled with the prescribed data. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.4"> Damage to containers and any other problem which might adversely affect the quality of a material should be investigated, recorded and reported to the Quality Control Department. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.5"> Incoming materials and finished products should be physically or administratively quarantined immediately after receipt or processing, until they have been released for use or distribution. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.6"> Intermediate and bulk products purchased as such should be handled on receipt as though they were starting materials. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.7"> All materials and products should be stored under the appropriate conditions established by the manufacturer and in an orderly fashion to permit batch segregation and stock rotation. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.8"> Checks on yields, and reconciliation of quantities, should be carried out as necessary to ensure that there are no discrepancies outside acceptable limits. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.9"> Operations on different products should not be carried out simultaneously or consecutively in the same room unless there is no risk of mix-up or cross-contamination. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.10"> At every stage of processing, products and materials should be protected from microbial and other contamination. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.11"> When working with dry materials and products, special precautions should be taken to prevent the generation and dissemination of dust. This applies particularly to the handling of highly active or sensitising materials. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.12"> At all times during processing, all materials, bulk containers, major items of equipment and where appropriate rooms used should be labelled or otherwise identified with an indication of the product or material being processed, its strength (where applicable) and batch number. Where applicable, this indication should also mention the stage of production. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.13"> Labels applied to containers, equipment or premises should be clear, unambiguous and in the company&#xfffd;s agreed format. It is often helpful in addition to the wording on the labels to use colours to indicate status (for example, quarantined, accepted, rejected, clean, ...). </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.14"> Checks should be carried out to ensure that pipelines and other pieces of equipment used for the transportation of products from one area to another are connected in a correct manner. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.15"> Any deviation from instructions or procedures should be avoided as far as possible. If a deviation occurs, it should be approved in writing by a competent person, with the involvement of the Quality Control Department when appropriate. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.16"> Access to production premises should be restricted to authorised personnel. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.17"> Normally, the production of non-medicinal products should be avoided in areas and with the equipment destined for the production of medicinal products</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title=" Prevention of cross-contamination in production"> Prevention of cross-contamination in production<paragraph paraNum="5.18"> Contamination of a starting material or of a product by another material or product must be avoided. This risk of accidental cross-contamination arises from the uncontrolled release of dust, gases, vapours, sprays or organisms from materials and products in process, from residues on equipment, and from operators&#xfffd; clothing. The significance of this risk varies with the type of contaminant and of product being contaminated. Amongst the most hazardous contaminants are highly sensitising materials, biological preparations containing living organisms, certain hormones, cytotoxics, and other highly active materials. Products in which contamination is likely to be most significant are those administered by injection, those given in large doses and/or over a long time. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.19"> Cross-contamination should be avoided by appropriate technical or organisational measures, for example: a) production in segregated areas (required for products such as penicillins, live vaccines, live bacterial preparations and some other biologicals), or by campaign (separation in time) followed by appropriate cleaning; b) providing appropriate air-locks and air extraction; c) minimising the risk of contamination caused by recirculation or re-entry of untreated or insufficiently treated air; d) keeping protective clothing inside areas where products with special risk of cross- contamination are processed; e) using cleaning and decontamination procedures of known effectiveness, as ineffective cleaning of equipment is a common source of cross-contamination; f) using &#xfffd;closed systems&amp;quot; of production; g) testing for residues and use of cleaning status labels on equipment. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.20"> Measures to prevent cross-contamination and their effectiveness should be checked periodically according to set procedures</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section title=" Validation"> Validation<paragraph paraNum="5.21"> Validation studies should reinforce Good Manufacturing Practice and be conducted in accordance with defined procedures. Results and conclusions should be recorded. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.22"> When any new manufacturing formula or method of preparation is adopted, steps should be taken to demonstrate its suitability for routine processing. The defined process, using the materials and equipment specified, should be shown to yield a product consistently of the required quality. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.23"> Significant amendments to the manufacturing process, including any change in equipment or materials, which may affect product quality and/or the reproducibility of the process should be validated. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.24"> Processes and procedures  should undergo periodic critical  re-validation to ensure that they remain capable of achieving the intended results</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title="Starting materials">Starting materials<paragraph paraNum="5.25"> The purchase of starting materials is an important operation which should involve staff who have a particular and thorough knowledge of the suppliers. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.26"> Starting materials should only be purchased from approved suppliers named in the relevant specification and, where possible, directly from the producer. It is recommended that the specifications established by the manufacturer for the starting materials be discussed with the suppliers. It is of benefit that all aspects of the production and control of the starting material in question, including handling, labelling and packaging requirements, as well as complaints and rejection procedures are discussed with the manufacturer and the supplier. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.27"> For each delivery, the containers should be checked for integrity of package and seal and for correspondence between the delivery note and the supplier&#xfffd;s labels. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.28"> If one material delivery is made up of different batches, each batch must be considered as separate for sampling, testing and release. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.29"> Starting materials in the storage area should be appropriately labelled (see Chapter 5, item 13). Labels should bear at least the following information: &#xfffd; the designated name of the product and the internal code reference where applicable; &#xfffd; a batch number given at receipt; &#xfffd; where appropriate, the status of the contents (e.g. in quarantine, on test, released, rejected); &#xfffd; where appropriate, an expiry date or a date beyond which retesting is necessary. When fully computerised storage systems are used, all the above information need not necessarily be in a legible form on the label. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.30"> There should be appropriate procedures or measures to assure the identity of the contents of each container of starting material. Bulk containers from which samples have been drawn should be identified (see Chapter 6, item 13). </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.31"> Only starting materials which have been released by the Quality Control Department and which are within their shelf life should be used. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.32"> Starting materials should only be dispensed by designated persons, following a written procedure, to ensure that the correct materials are accurately weighed or measured into clean and properly labelled containers. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.33"> Each dispensed material and its weight or volume should be independently checked and the check recorded. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.34"> Materials dispensed for each batch should be kept together and conspicuously labelled as such</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title="Processing operations: intermediate and bulk products">Processing operations: intermediate and bulk products<paragraph paraNum="5.35"> Before any processing operation is started, steps should be taken to ensure that the work area and equipment are clean and free from any starting materials, products, product residues or documents not required for the current operation. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.36"> Intermediate and bulk products should be kept under appropriate conditions. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.37"> Critical processes should be validated (see &amp;quot;VALIDATION&amp;quot; in this Chapter). </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.38"> Any necessary in-process controls and environmental controls should be carried out and recorded. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.39"> Any significant deviation from the expected yield should be recorded and investigated</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title="Packaging materials">Packaging materials<paragraph paraNum="5.40"> The purchase, handling and control of primary and printed packaging materials shall be accorded attention similar to that given to starting materials. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.41"> Particular attention should be paid to printed materials. They should be stored in adequately secure conditions such as to exclude unauthorised access. Cut labels and other loose printed materials should be stored and transported in separate closed containers so as to avoid mix-ups. Packaging materials should be issued for use only by authorised personnel following an approved and documented procedure. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.42"> Each delivery or batch of printed or primary packaging material should be given a specific reference number or identification mark. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.43"> Outdated or obsolete primary packaging material or printed packaging material should be destroyed and this disposal recorded</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title="Packaging operations">Packaging operations<paragraph paraNum="5.44"> When setting up a programme for the packaging operations, particular attention should be given to minimising the risk of cross-contamination, mix-ups or substitutions. Different products should not be packaged in close proximity unless there is physical segregation. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.45"> Before packaging operations are begun, steps should be taken to ensure that the work area, packaging lines, printing machines and other equipment are clean and free from any products, materials or documents previously used, if these are not required for the current operation. The line-clearance should be performed according to an appropriate check-list. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.46"> The name and batch number of the product being handled should be displayed at each packaging station or line. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.47"> All products and packaging materials to be used should be checked on delivery to the packaging department for quantity, identity and conformity with the Packaging Instructions. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.48"> Containers for filling should be clean before filling. Attention should be given to avoiding and removing any contaminants such as glass fragments and metal particles. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.49"> Normally, filling and sealing should be followed as quickly as possible by labelling. If it is not the case, appropriate procedures should be applied to ensure that no mix-ups or mislabelling can occur. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.50"> The correct performance of any printing operation (for example code numbers, expiry dates) to be done separately or in the course of the packaging should be checked and recorded. Attention should be paid to printing by hand which should be re-checked at regular intervals. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.51"> Special care should be taken when using cut-labels and when over-printing is carried out off-line. Roll-feed labels are normally preferable to cut-labels, in helping to avoid mix-ups. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.52"> Checks should be made to ensure that any electronic code readers, label counters or similar devices are operating correctly. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.53"> Printed and embossed information on packaging materials should be distinct and resistant to fading or erasing. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.54"> On-line control of the product during packaging should include at least checking the following: a) general appearance of the packages; b) whether the packages are complete; c) whether the correct products and packaging materials are used; d) whether any over-printing is correct; e) correct functioning of line monitors. Samples taken away from the packaging line should not be returned. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.55"> Products which have been involved in an unusual event should only be reintroduced into the process after special inspection, investigation and approval by authorised personnel. Detailed record should be kept of this operation. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.56"> Any significant or unusual discrepancy observed during reconciliation of the amount of bulk product and printed packaging materials and the number of units produced should be investigated and satisfactorily accounted for before release. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.57"> Upon completion of a packaging operation, any unused batch-coded packaging materials should be destroyed and the destruction recorded. A documented procedure should be followed if uncoded printed materials are returned to stock</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title="Finished products">Finished products<paragraph paraNum="5.58"> Finished products should be held in quarantine until their final release under conditions established by the manufacturer. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.59"> The evaluation of finished products and documentation which is necessary before release of product for sale are described in Chapter 6 (Quality Control). </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.60"> After release, finished products should be stored as usable stock under conditions established by the manufacturer</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section
                    title="Rejected, recovered and returned materials">Rejected, recovered and returned materials<paragraph paraNum="5.61"> Rejected materials and products should be clearly marked as such and stored separately in restricted areas. They should either be returned to the suppliers or, where appropriate, reprocessed or destroyed. Whatever action is taken should be approved and recorded by authorised personnel. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.62"> The reprocessing of rejected products should be exceptional. It is only permitted if the quality of the final product is not affected, if the specifications are met and if it is done in accordance with a defined and authorised procedure after evaluation of the risks involved. Record should be kept of the reprocessing. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.63"> The recovery of all or part of earlier batches which conform to the required quality by incorporation into a batch of the same product at a defined stage of manufacture should be authorised beforehand. This recovery should be carried out in accordance with a defined procedure after evaluation of the risks involved, including any possible effect on shelf life. The recovery should be recorded. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.64"> The need for additional testing of any finished product which has been reprocessed, or into which a recovered product has been incorporated, should be considered by the Quality Control Department. </paragraph>
                <paragraph paraNum="5.65"> Products returned from the market and which have left the control of the manufacturer should be destroyed unless without doubt their quality is satisfactory; they may be considered for re-sale, re-labelling or recovery in a subsequent batch only after they have been critically assessed by the Quality Control Department in accordance with a written procedure. The nature of the product, any special storage conditions it requires, its condition and history, and the time elapsed since it was issued should all be taken into account in this assessment. Where any doubt arises over the quality of the product, it should not be considered suitable for re-issue or re-use, although basic chemical re- processing to recover active ingredient may be possible. Any action taken should be appropriately recorded</paragraph>
            </section>
        </chapter>
    </content>
</document>
