<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> If a material is subdivided for later use in production operations, the container  receiving the material should be suitable and should be so identified that the following  information is available: </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Material name and/or item code;  - Receiving or control number;  - Weight or measure of material in the new container; and  - Re-evaluation or retest date if appropriate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> Critical weighing, measuring, or subdividing operations should be witnessed  or subjected to an equivalent control. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> Prior to use, production personnel should verify  that the materials are those specified in the batch record for the intended intermediate  or API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Other critical activities should be witnessed or subjected to an equivalent  control. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> Actual yields should be compared with expected yields at designated steps in  the production process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> Expected yields with appropriate ranges should be established  based on previous laboratory, pilot scale, or manufacturing data. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> Deviations in yield  associated with critical process steps should be investigated to determine their impact  or potential impact on the resulting quality of affected batches. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> Any deviation should be documented and explained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> Any critical deviation  should be investigated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> The processing status of major units of equipment should be indicated either  on the individual units of equipment or by appropriate documentation, computer  control systems, or alternative means. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> If time limits are specified in the master production instruction (see 6.41),  these time limits should be met to ensure the quality of intermediates and APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> Deviations should be documented and evaluated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> Time limits may be inappropriate  when processing to a target value (e.g., pH adjustment, hydrogenation, drying to  predetermined specification) because completion of reactions or processing steps are  determined by in-process sampling and testing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> Intermediates held for further processing should be stored under appropriate  conditions to ensure their suitability for use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> Written procedures should be established to monitor the progress and control  the performance of processing steps that cause variability in the quality characteristics  of intermediates and APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> In-process controls and their acceptance criteria should be  defined based on the information gained during the development stage or historical  data. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> The acceptance criteria and type and extent of testing can depend on the nature  of the intermediate or API being manufactured, the reaction or process step being  conducted, and the degree to which the process introduces variability in the product’s  quality. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Less stringent in-process controls may be appropriate in early processing  steps, whereas tighter controls may be appropriate for later processing steps (e.g.,  isolation and purification steps). </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> Critical in-process controls (and critical process monitoring), including the  control points and methods, should be stated in writing and approved by the quality  unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> In-process controls can be performed by qualified production department  personnel and the process adjusted without prior quality unit(s) approval if the  adjustments are made within pre-established limits approved by the quality unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> All tests and results should be fully documented as part of the batch record. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Written procedures should describe the sampling methods for in-process  materials, intermediates, and APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> Sampling plans and procedures should be based  on scientifically sound sampling practices. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> In-process sampling should be conducted using procedures designed to  prevent contamination of the sampled material and other intermediates or APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> Procedures should be established to ensure the integrity of samples after collection. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> For the purpose of this document, blending is defined as the process of  combining materials within the same specification to produce a homogeneous  intermediate or API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> In-process mixing of fractions from single batches (e.g.,  collecting several centrifuge loads from a single crystallization batch) or combining  fractions from several batches for further processing is considered to be part of the  production process and is not considered to be blending. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> Out-Of-Specification batches should not be blended with other batches for the  purpose of meeting specifications. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> Each batch incorporated into the blend should have  been manufactured using an established process and should have been individually  tested and found to meet appropriate specifications prior to blending. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> Acceptable blending operations include but are not limited to:  - Blending of small batches to increase batch size  - Blending of tailings (i.e., relatively small quantities of isolated material) from  batches of the same intermediate orAPItoforma single batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Blending processes should be adequately controlled and documented and the  blended batch should be tested for conformance to established specifications where  appropriate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> The batch record of the blending process should allow traceability back to the  individual batches that make up the blend. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> Where physical attributes of the API are critical (e.g., APIs intended for use in  solid oral dosage forms or suspensions), blending operations should be validated to  show homogeneity of the combined batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> Validation should include testing of critical  attributes (e.g., particle size distribution, bulk density, and tap density) that may be  affected by the blending process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> If the blending could adversely affect stability, stability testing of the final  blended batches should be performed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> The expiry or retest date of the blended batch should be based on the  manufacturing date of the oldest tailings or batch in the blend. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Residual materials can be carried over into successive batches of the same  intermediate or API if there is adequate control. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> Examples include residue adhering to  the wall of a micronizer, residual layer of damp crystals remaining in a centrifuge   28 bowl after discharge, and incomplete discharge of fluids or crystals from a processing  vessel upon transfer of the material to the next step in the process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> Such carryover  should not result in the carryover of degradants or microbial contamination that may  adversely alter the established API impurity profile. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> Production operations should be conducted in a manner that will prevent  contamination of intermediates or APIs by other materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Precautions to avoid contamination should be taken when APIs are handled after  purification. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> There should be written procedures describing the receipt, identification,  quarantine, sampling, examination and/or testing and release, and handling of  packaging and labelling materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> Packaging and labelling materials should conform to established  specifications. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> Those that do not comply with such specifications should be rejected  to prevent their use in operations for which they are unsuitable. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> Records should be maintained for each shipment of labels and packaging  materials showing receipt, examination, or testing, and whether accepted or rejected. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> Containers should provide adequate protection against deterioration or  contamination of the intermediate or API that may occur during transportation and  recommended storage. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> Containers should be clean and, where indicated by the nature of the  intermediate or API, sanitized to ensure that they are suitable for their intended use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> These containers should not be reactive, additive, or absorptive so as to alter the  quality of the intermediate or API beyond the specified limits. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> If containers are re-used, they should be cleaned in accordance with  documented procedures and all previous labels should be removed or defaced. </sentence>
</sentences>
