<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> Equipment cleaning/sanitization studies should address microbiological and  endotoxin contamination for those processes where there is a need to reduce total  microbiological count or endotoxins in the API, or other processes where such  contamination could be of concern (e.g., non-sterile APIs used to manufacture sterile  products). </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Cleaning procedures should be monitored at appropriate intervals after  validation to ensure that these procedures are effective when used during routine  production. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> Equipment cleanliness can be monitored by analytical testing and visual  examination, where feasible. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> Visual inspection can allow detection of gross  contamination concentrated in small areas that could otherwise go undetected by  sampling and/or analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Analytical methods should be validated unless the method employed is  included in the relevant pharmacopoeia or other recognised standard reference. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> The  suitability of all testing methods used should nonetheless be verified under actual  conditions of use and documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> Methods should be validated to include consideration of characteristics  included within the ICH guidelines on validation of analytical methods. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> The degree of  analytical validation performed should reflect the purpose of the analysis and the  stage of the API production process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> Appropriate qualification of analytical equipment should be considered before  starting validation of analytical methods. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> Complete records should be maintained of any modification of a validated  analytical method. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> Such records should include the reason for the modification and  appropriate data to verify that the modification produces results that are as accurate  and reliable as the established method. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> Intermediates and APIs failing to meet established specifications should be  identified as such and quarantined. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> These intermediates or APIs can be reprocessed or  reworked as described below. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> The final disposition of rejected materials should be  recorded. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> Introducing an intermediate or API, including one that does not conform to  standards or specifications, back into the process and reprocessing by repeating a  crystallization step or other appropriate chemical or physical manipulation steps (e.g.,  distillation, filtration, chromatography, milling) that are part of the established  manufacturing process is generally considered acceptable. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> However, if such   40 reprocessing is used for a majority of batches, such reprocessing should be included  as part of the standard manufacturing process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> Continuation of a process step after an in-process control test has shown that  the step is incomplete is considered to be part of the normal process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> This is not  considered to be reprocessing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Introducing unreacted material back into a process and repeating a chemical  reaction is considered to be reprocessing unless it is part of the established process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> Such reprocessing should be preceded by careful evaluation to ensure that the quality  of the intermediate or API is not adversely impacted due to the potential formation of  by-products and over-reacted materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> Before a decision is taken to rework batches that do not conform to established  standards or specifications, an investigation into the reason for non-conformance  should be performed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> Batches that have been reworked should be subjected to appropriate  evaluation, testing, stability testing if warranted, and documentation to show that the  reworked product is of equivalent quality to that produced by the original process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Concurrent validation is often the appropriate validation approach for rework  procedures. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> This allows a protocol to define the rework procedure, how it will be  carried out, and the expected results. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> If there is only one batch to be reworked, then a  report can be written and the batch released once it is found to be acceptable. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> Procedures should provide for comparing the impurity profile of each  reworked batch against batches manufactured by the established process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> Where  routine analytical methods are inadequate to characterize the reworked batch,  additional methods should be used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> Recovery (e.g. from mother liquor or filtrates) of reactants, intermediates, or  the API is considered acceptable, provided that approved procedures exist for the  recovery and the recovered materials meet specifications suitable for their intended  use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> Solvents can be recovered and reused in the same processes or in different  processes, provided that the recovery procedures are controlled and monitored to  ensure that solvents meet appropriate standards before reuse or co-mingling with  other approved materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> Fresh and recovered solvents and reagents can be combined if adequate testing  has shown their suitability for all manufacturing processes in which they may be used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> Returned intermediates or APIs should be identified as such and quarantined. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> If the conditions under which returned intermediates or APIs have been stored  or shipped before or during their return or the condition of their containers casts doubt  on their quality, the returned intermediates or APIs should be reprocessed, reworked,  or destroyed, as appropriate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> Records of returned intermediates or APIs should be maintained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> For each  return, documentation should include: </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> Name and address of the consignee  - Intermediate or API, batch number, and quantity returned  - Reason for return  - Use or disposal of the returned intermediate or API </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> This section applies to any party other than the original manufacturer who may  trade and/or take possession, repack, relabel, manipulate, distribute or store an API or  intermediate. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> All agents, brokers, traders, distributors, repackers, and relabellers should  comply with GMP as defined in this Guide. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Agents, brokers, traders, distributors, repackers, or relabellers should maintain  complete traceability of APIs and intermediates that they distribute. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> Documents that  should be retained and available include: </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> Identity of original manufacturer  - Address of original manufacturer  - Purchase orders  - Bills of lading (transportation documentation)  - Receipt documents  - Name or designation of API or intermediate  - Manufacturer’s batch number  - Transportation and distribution records  - All authentic Certificates of Analysis, including those of the original  manufacturer  - Retest or expiry date </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> Agents, brokers, traders, distributors, repackers, or relabellers should establish,  document and implement an effective system of managing quality, as specified in  Section 2. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Repackaging, relabelling and holding of APIs and intermediates should be  performed under appropriate GMP controls, as stipulated in this Guide, to avoid mix- ups and loss of API or intermediate identity or purity. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> Repackaging should be conducted under appropriate environmental conditions  to avoid contamination and cross-contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> Stability studies to justify assigned expiration or retest dates should be  conducted if the API or intermediate is repackaged in a different type of container  than that used by the API or intermediate manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> Agents, brokers, distributors, repackers, or relabellers should transfer all  quality or regulatory information received from an API or intermediate manufacturer  to the customer, and from the customer to the API or intermediate manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> The agent, broker, trader, distributor, repacker, or relabeller who supplies the  API or intermediate to the customer should provide the name of the original API or  intermediate manufacturer and the batch number(s) supplied. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> The agent should also provide the identity of the original API or intermediate  manufacturer to regulatory authorities upon request. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> The original manufacturer can  respond to the regulatory authority directly or through its authorized agents,  depending on the legal relationship between the authorized agents and the original  API or intermediate manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="49">(In this context "authorized" refers to authorized  by the manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> </sentence>
</sentences>
