<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> Access to the label storage areas should be limited to authorised personnel. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Procedures should be used to reconcile the quantities of labels issued, used,  and returned and to evaluate discrepancies found between the number of containers   29 labelled and the number of labels issued. </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> Such discrepancies should be investigated,  and the investigation should be approved by the quality unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> All excess labels bearing batch numbers or other batch-related printing should  be destroyed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> Returned labels should be maintained and stored in a manner that  prevents mix-ups and provides proper identification. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> Obsolete and out-dated labels should be destroyed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> Printing devices used to print labels for packaging operations should be  controlled to ensure that all imprinting conforms to the print specified in the batch  production record. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> Printed labels issued for a batch should be carefully examined for proper  identity and conformity to specifications in the master production record. </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> The results  of this examination should be documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> A printed label representative of those used should be included in the batch  production record. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> There should be documented procedures designed to ensure that correct  packaging materials and labels are used. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> Labelling operations should be designed to prevent mix-ups. </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> There should be  physical or spatial separation from operations involving other intermediates or APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> Labels used on containers of intermediates or APIs should indicate the name  or identifying code, the batch number of the product, and storage conditions, when  such information is critical to assure the quality of intermediate or API. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> If the intermediate or API is intended to be transferred outside the control of  the manufacturer‚Äôs material management system, the name and address of the  manufacturer, quantity of contents, and special transport conditions and any special  legal requirements should also be included on the label. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> For intermediates or APIs  with an expiry date, the expiry date should be indicated on the label and Certificate of  Analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> For intermediates or APIs with a retest date, the retest date should be  indicated on the label and/or Certificate of Analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> Packaging and labelling facilities should be inspected immediately before use  to ensure that all materials not needed for the next packaging operation have been  removed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> This examination should be documented in the batch production records,  the facility log, or other documentation system. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> Packaged and labelled intermediates or APIs should be examined to ensure  that containers and packages in the batch have the correct label. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> This examination  should be part of the packaging operation. </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> Results of these examinations should be  recorded in the batch production or control records. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> Facilities should be available for the storage of all materials under appropriate  conditions (e.g. controlled temperature and humidity when necessary). </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> Records  should be maintained of these conditions if they are critical for the maintenance of  material characteristics. </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> Unless there is an alternative system to prevent the unintentional or  unauthorised use of quarantined, rejected, returned, or recalled materials, separate  storage areas should be assigned for their temporary storage until the decision as to  their future use has been taken. </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> APIs and intermediates should only be released for distribution to third parties  after they have been released by the quality unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> APIs and intermediates can be  transferred under quarantine to another unit under the company‚Äôs control when  authorized by the quality unit(s) and if appropriate controls and documentation are in  place. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> APIs and intermediates should be transported in a manner that does not  adversely affect their quality. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> Special transport or storage conditions for an API or intermediate should be  stated on the label. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> The manufacturer should ensure that the contract acceptor (contractor) for  transportation of the API or intermediate knows and follows the appropriate transport  and storage conditions. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> A system should be in place by which the distribution of each batch of  intermediate and/or API can be readily determined to permit its recall. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> The independent quality unit(s) should have at its disposal adequate laboratory  facilities. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> Laboratory records should be maintained in accordance with Section 6.6. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> All specifications, sampling plans, and test procedures should be scientifically  sound and appropriate to ensure that raw materials, intermediates, APIs, and labels  and packaging materials conform to established standards of quality and/or purity. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> Specifications and test procedures should be consistent with those included in the  registration/filing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> There can be specifications in addition to those in the  registration/filing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> Specifications, sampling plans, and test procedures, including  changes to them, should be drafted by the appropriate organizational unit and  reviewed and approved by the quality unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Appropriate specifications should be established for APIs in accordance with  accepted standards and consistent with the manufacturing process. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> The specifications  should include a control of the impurities (e.g. organic impurities, inorganic  impurities, and residual solvents). </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> If the API has a specification for microbiological  purity, appropriate action limits for total microbial counts and objectionable  organisms should be established and met. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> If the API has a specification for  endotoxins, appropriate action limits should be established and met. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Laboratory controls should be followed and documented at the time of  performance. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> Any departures from the above described procedures should be  documented and explained. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> Any out-of-specification result obtained should be investigated and  documented according to a procedure. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> This procedure should require analysis of the  data, assessment of whether a significant problem exists, allocation of the tasks for  corrective actions, and conclusions. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> Any re-sampling and/or retesting after OOS  results should be performed according to a documented procedure. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> Reagents and standard solutions should be prepared and labelled following  written procedures. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48">úUse by‚Äù dates should be applied as appropriate for analytical  reagents or standard solutions. </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> Primary reference standards should be obtained as appropriate for the  manufacture of APIs. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> The source of each primary reference standard should be  documented. </sentence>
</sentences>
