<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sentences>
    <sentence count="1"> In continuous production, the product code  together with the date and time can serve as the unique identifier until the final  number is allocated. </sentence>
    <sentence count="2"> Documentation of completion of each significant step in the batch production  records (batch production and control records) should include: </sentence>
    <sentence count="3"> Dates and, when appropriate, times;   21 - Identity of major equipment (e.g., reactors, driers, mills, etc.) used;  - Specific identification of each batch, including weights, measures, and batch  numbers of raw materials, intermediates, or any reprocessed materials used  during manufacturing;  - Actual results recorded for critical process parameters;  - Any sampling performed;  - Signatures of the persons performing and directly supervising or checking  each critical step in the operation;  - In-process and laboratory test results;  - Actual yield at appropriate phases or times;  - Description of packaging and label for intermediate or API;  - Representative label of API or intermediate if made commercially available;  - Any deviation noted, its evaluation, investigation conducted (if appropriate)  or reference to that investigation if stored separately; and  - Results of release testing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="4"> Written procedures should be established and followed for investigating  critical deviations or the failure of a batch of intermediate or API to meet  specifications. </sentence>
    <sentence count="5"> The investigation should extend to other batches that may have been  associated with the specific failure or deviation. </sentence>
    <sentence count="6"> Laboratory control records should include complete data derived from all tests  conducted to ensure compliance with established specifications and standards,  including examinations and assays, as follows: </sentence>
    <sentence count="7"> A description of samples received for testing, including the material name or  source, batch number or other distinctive code, date sample was taken, and,  where appropriate, the quantity and date the sample was received for testing;  - A statement of or reference to each test method used;  - A statement of the weight or measure of sample used for each test as  described by the method; data on or cross-reference to the preparation and  testing of reference standards, reagents and standard solutions,  - A complete record of all raw data generated during each test, in addition to  graphs, charts, and spectra from laboratory instrumentation, properly  identified to show the specific material and batch tested;  - A record of all calculations performed in connection with the test, including,  for example, units of measure, conversion factors, and equivalency factors;  - A statement of the test results and how they compare with established  acceptance criteria;   22 - The signature of the person who performed each test and the date(s) the tests  were performed; and  - The date and signature of a second person showing that the original records  have been reviewed for accuracy, completeness, and compliance with  established standards. </sentence>
    <sentence count="8"> Complete records should also be maintained for: </sentence>
    <sentence count="9"> Any modifications to an established analytical method,  - Periodic calibration of laboratory instruments, apparatus, gauges, and  recording devices;  - All stability testing performed on APIs; and  - Out-of-specification (OOS) investigations. </sentence>
    <sentence count="10"> Written procedures should be established and followed for the review and  approval of batch production and laboratory control records, including packaging and  labelling, to determine compliance of the intermediate or API with established  specifications before a batch is released or distributed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="11"> Batch production and laboratory control records of critical process steps  should be reviewed and approved by the quality unit(s) before an API batch is  released or distributed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="12"> Production and laboratory control records of non-critical  process steps can be reviewed by qualified production personnel or other units  following procedures approved by the quality unit(s). </sentence>
    <sentence count="13"> All deviation, investigation, and OOS reports should be reviewed as part of the  batch record review before the batch is released. </sentence>
    <sentence count="14"> The quality unit(s) can delegate to the production unit the responsibility and  authority for release of intermediates, except for those shipped outside the control of  the manufacturing company. </sentence>
    <sentence count="15"> There should be written procedures describing the receipt, identification,  quarantine, storage, handling, sampling, testing, and approval or rejection of  materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="16"> Manufacturers of intermediates and/or APIs should have a system for  evaluating the suppliers of critical materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="17"> If the supplier of a critical material is not the manufacturer of that material, the  name and address of that manufacturer should be known by the intermediate and/or  API manufacturer. </sentence>
    <sentence count="18"> Changing the source of supply of critical raw materials should be treated  according to Section 13, Change Control. </sentence>
    <sentence count="19"> Upon receipt and before acceptance, each container or grouping of containers  of materials should be examined visually for correct labelling (including correlation  between the name used by the supplier and the in-house name, if these are different),  container damage, broken seals and evidence of tampering or contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="20"> Materials should be held under quarantine until they have been sampled, examined or  tested as appropriate, and released for use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="21"> Before incoming materials are mixed with existing stocks (e.g., solvents or  stocks in silos), they should be identified as correct, tested, if appropriate, and  released. </sentence>
    <sentence count="22"> Procedures should be available to prevent discharging incoming materials  wrongly into the existing stock. </sentence>
    <sentence count="23"> If bulk deliveries are made in non-dedicated tankers, there should be assurance  of no cross-contamination from the tanker. </sentence>
    <sentence count="24"> Means of providing this assurance could  include one or more of the following: </sentence>
    <sentence count="25"> </sentence>
    <sentence count="26"> Large storage containers, and their attendant manifolds, filling and discharge  lines should be appropriately identified. </sentence>
    <sentence count="27"> Each container or grouping of containers (batches) of materials should be  assigned and identified with a distinctive code, batch, or receipt number. </sentence>
    <sentence count="28"> This number  should be used in recording the disposition of each batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="29"> A system should be in place  to identify the status of each batch. </sentence>
    <sentence count="30"> At least one test to verify the identity of each batch of material should be  conducted, with the exception of the materials described below in 7.32. </sentence>
    <sentence count="31"> A supplier's  Certificate of Analysis can be used in place of performing other tests, provided that  the manufacturer has a system in place to evaluate suppliers. </sentence>
    <sentence count="32"> Full analyses should be conducted on at least three  batches before reducing in-house testing. </sentence>
    <sentence count="33"> However, as a minimum, a full analysis  should be performed at appropriate intervals and compared with the Certificates of  Analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="34"> Reliability of Certificates of Analysis should be checked at regular  intervals. </sentence>
    <sentence count="35"> Processing aids, hazardous or highly toxic raw materials, other special  materials, or materials transferred to another unit within the company’s control do not  need to be tested if the manufacturer’s Certificate of Analysis is obtained, showing  that these raw materials conform to established specifications. </sentence>
    <sentence count="36"> Visual examination of  containers, labels, and recording of batch numbers should help in establishing the  identity of these materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="37"> The lack of on-site testing for these materials should be  justified and documented. </sentence>
    <sentence count="38"> Samples should be representative of the batch of material from which they are  taken. </sentence>
    <sentence count="39"> Sampling methods should specify the number of containers to be sampled, which part  of the container to sample, and the amount of material to be taken from each  container. </sentence>
    <sentence count="40"> The number of containers to sample and the sample size should be based  upon a sampling plan that takes into consideration the criticality of the material,  material variability, past quality history of the supplier, and the quantity needed for  analysis. </sentence>
    <sentence count="41"> Sampling should be conducted at defined locations and by procedures  designed to prevent contamination of the material sampled and contamination of other  materials. </sentence>
    <sentence count="42"> Containers from which samples are withdrawn should be opened carefully and  subsequently reclosed. </sentence>
    <sentence count="43"> They should be marked to indicate that a sample has been  taken. </sentence>
    <sentence count="44"> Materials should be handled and stored in a manner to prevent degradation,  contamination, and cross-contamination. </sentence>
    <sentence count="45"> Materials stored in fiber drums, bags, or boxes should be stored off the floor  and, when appropriate, suitably spaced to permit cleaning and inspection. </sentence>
    <sentence count="46"> Materials should be stored under conditions and for a period that have no  adverse affect on their quality, and should normally be controlled so that the oldest  stock is used first. </sentence>
    <sentence count="47"> Certain materials in suitable containers can be stored outdoors, provided  identifying labels remain legible and containers are appropriately cleaned before  opening and use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="48"> Materials should be re-evaluated as appropriate to determine their suitability  for use (e.g., after prolonged storage or exposure to heat or humidity). </sentence>
    <sentence count="49"> Raw materials for intermediate and API manufacturing should be weighed or  measured under appropriate conditions that do not affect their suitability for use. </sentence>
    <sentence count="50"> Weighing and measuring devices should be of suitable accuracy for the intended use. </sentence>
</sentences>
