<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<meta>
<name> Eudralex</name>
<description> EU regulation for the pharmaceutical industry </description>
<body>EMEA</body>
<version> 1.0 </version>
<published_on> 2007 </published_on>
</meta>
<chapter id="5"> <title>Chapter 5 Production </title>
<section id="5.2"> <title> Process Equipement </title>
 <subsection id="5.20"> <title> Equipment Maintainance and Cleaning </title>
	<regulation id="5.21">
		<sentence count="1"> 5.21 Written procedures should be established for cleaning of equipment and its subsequent release for use in the manufacture of intermediates and APIs </sentence>
		<sentence count="2"> Cleaning procedures should contain sufficient details to enable operators to clean each type of equipment in a reproducible and effective manner. </sentence>
		<sentence count="3"> These procedures should include:</sentence>
		<sentence count="4"> Assignment of responsibility for cleaning of equipment;</sentence>
		<sentence count="5"> Cleaning schedules, including, where appropriate, sanitizing schedules;</sentence>
		<sentence count="6"> A complete description of the methods and materials, including dilution of cleaning agents used to clean equipment;</sentence>
		<sentence count="7"> When appropriate, instructions for disassembling and reassembling each article of equipment to ensure proper cleaning;</sentence>
		<sentence count="8"> Instructions for the removal or obliteration of previous batch identification;</sentence>
		<sentence count="9"> Instructions for the removal or obliteration of previous batch identification;</sentence>
		<sentence count="10"> Instructions for the protection of clean equipment from contamination prior to use;</sentence>
		<sentence count="11"> Inspection of equipment for cleanliness immediately before use, if practical;and</sentence>
		<sentence count="12"> Establishing the maximum time that may elapse between the completion of processing and equipment cleaning, when appropriate.</sentence>
	</regulation>
	<regulation id="5.22">
		<sentence count="1"> 5.22 Equipment and utensils should be cleaned, stored, and, where appropriate, sanitized or sterilized to prevent contamination or carry-over of a material that would alter the quality of the intermediate or API beyond the official or other established specfications.</sentence>
	</regulation>
 </subsection>
</section>	
<section id="5.3"> <title> Process </title>
 <subsection id="5.30"> <title> Starting Material </title>
	<regulation id="5.26">
		<sentence count="1"> 5.26 Starting materials should only be purchased from approved suppliers named in the relevant specification, and where possible, directly from the producer.It is recommended that the specifications established by the manufacturer for starting materials be discussed with the suppliers.</sentence>
	</regulation>
	<regulation id="5.31">	
		<sentence count="1"> 5.31 Only starting materials which have been released by the Quality Control Department and which are within their shelf life should be used. </sentence>
	</regulation>
 </subsection>
</section>	
<section id="8"> <title> Production and In-Process Controls </title>
 <subsection id="8.1"> <title> Production Operations </title>
	<regulation id="8.14">	
		<sentence count="1">  8.14 Actual yields should be compared with expeected yields at designated steps in the production process. </sentence>

	   <sentence count="2"> Expected yields should be established on previous laboratory, pilot scale, or manufacturing data. </sentence>
		
		<sentence count="3"> Deviations in yield associated witj designated process steps should be investigated to determine their impact or potential impact on the resulting quality of affected batches.</sentence>  
	</regulation>
 </subsection>
</section>
</chapter>
</document>